Guide to the William Leonard Albrecht Papers 1880-1968
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
- Gold Black Sand Mining Company, 1921-1936; Series II; 0.25 linear feet
  - General Correspondence, 1923-1936; Subseries 1; 0.25 linear feet
    - 1927 (Box-folder 85/8)
    - 1927-1930, 1936 (Box-folder 85/9)
  - Legal and Organizational, 1921-1932; Subseries 2; 4 folders
    - Legal Documents, 1925-1928 (Box-folder 85/10)
    - Organizational Papers, 1924-1932 (Box-folder 85/11)
    - Reports, 1921-1924 (Box-folder 85/12)
    - Fragments of Interoffice Materials, undated (Box-folder 85/13)
  - Clippings, 1927; Subseries 3; 1 folder
    - Clippings, 1927 (Box-folder 85/14)
- Sons of Hermann, Bismarck Lodge No. 1, 1892-1893 and 1928; Series III; 1 folder and 4 oversize volumes
  This series contains financial and organizational records generated by the Sons of Hermann, Bismarck Lodge No. 1 and its subsidiary operation, the Montana Herold Publishing Company. The Sons of Hermann had its origin as a mutual protection society for German immigrants to New York City in the 1840s, but in Great Falls served more as a cultural preservation and business networking organization. The Montana Herold was a German language newspaper published in Great Falls from 1892 to 1898. Included with these materials is a list of subscribers that may be of great interest to genealogical researchers.
  - Financial, 1928; Subseries 1; 1 folder
    - Financial Records, 1928 (Box-folder 85/15)
  - Montana Herold Publishing Company, 1892-1893; Subseries 2; 4 oversize volumes
    - General Journal, 1892-1893 (Volume 114)
    - General Ledger, 1892-1893 (Volume 115)
    - Stock Book, 1892 (Volume 116)
    - Day Book, List of Subscribers, Exchanges, 1892-1893 (Volume 117)
- German Lodge, Great Falls, 1888-1911; Series IV; 4 oversize volumes
  This series contains 4 volumes of organizational and financial records generated by the German Lodge of Great Falls, a fraternal organization composed of German-American immigrants and descendents.
  - Minutes, 1888-1891 (Volume 118)
  - Ledger, 1889-1891 (Volume 119)
  - Ledger, 1908-1911 (Volume 120)
  - Day Book, 1906-1908 (Volume 121)
- Cascade and Bitter Root Lumber Company, 1891-1897; Series V; 6 oversize volumes
  This series contains six volumes of correspondence and financial records from the Cascade and Bitter Root Lumber Company, a late 19th century raw timber distributor that conducted extensive business with the Anaconda Copper Mining Company but also supplied several other Montana operations and a few midwestern furniture manufactures.
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1896-1897 (Volume 122)
  - Journal, 1896-1897 (Volume 123)
  - General Ledger, 1896-1897 (Volume 124)
  - Petty Cash, 1896-1897 (Volume 125)
  - Stock Book, 1896-1897 (Volume 126)
  - Unidentified Cash Book, 1891-1892 (Volume 127)
- Photographs, circa 1880 - circa 1960; Series VI; 24 items
  This series contains 19 images of late 19th century Great Falls, Montana, including some buildings now listed on the National Register of Historic sites. These images document several early Great Falls businesses and the character of the downtown district just prior to 1900. Also included in this series are three candid images of William Albrecht, junior, one professional portrait of William Albrecht, senior, that hung in the furniture store, and one photograph of an Albrecht Furniture billboard from the mid 1960s.
  - Architect’s rendering for William A. Albrecht Furniture store, Great Falls, Montana, undated (Box xx, Photo number 75-5985)
  - Cataract Grain Mill, exterior, Great Falls, Montana, circa 1880-1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-5986)
  - Interior of butcher shop, Great Falls, Montana, circa 1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-5987)
  - Drawing of First National Bank Building, Great Falls, Montana, circa 1880-1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-5988)
  - Corner shot of Phelps Block, Great Falls, Montana, circa 1880-1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-5989)
  - Fountain and Park at end of Central Avenue, Great Falls, Montana, circa 1880-1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-5990)
  - Unidentified building in Great Falls, Montana, Streetcar in foreground, circa 1880-1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-5991)
  - W. B. Raleigh and Company dry goods store, Montana, circa 1900 (Box xx, Photo number 75-5992)
  - Parade, Murphy-Maclay Hardware in background, Great Falls, Montana, circa 1880-1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-5993)
  - Exterior view of Grand Hotel, Great Falls, Montana, circa 1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-5994)
  - Drawing of the Rainbow Hotel, Great Falls, Montana, circa 1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-5995)
  - Feed Stable, H. P. Nevills, Proprietor. Large picture of elephant and bunting displayed above sign, Great Falls, Montana, circa 1880-1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-5996)
  - Bachcory and Company Building under construction, Great Falls, Montana, circa 1880-1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-5997)
  - Smelter in Great Falls, Montana, circa 1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-5998)
  - Unidentified building, Great Falls, Montana, circa 1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-5999)
  - Central Avenue looking east, Great Falls, Montana, 1887 (Box xx, Photo number 75-6000)
  - Park Hotel in Great Falls, Montana, circa 1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-6001)
  - Hospital in Great Falls, Montana, circa 1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-6002)
  - Exterior of William Albrecht Furniture Company, Great Falls, Montana, circa 1880-1890 (Box xx, Photo number 75-6003)
  - William A. Albrecht, undated (Box-folder 85/16, Photo number 50(VI):1)
  - William A. Albrecht playing organ, 1942 (Box-folder 85/16, Photo number 50(VI):2)
  - William A. Albrecht, 1942 (Box-folder 85/16, Photo number 50(VI):3)
  - Albrecht Furniture Company Billboard, Great Falls, Montana, 1964 (Box-folder 85/16, Photo number 50(VI):4)
  - William L. Albrecht, oversize framed portrait [hung in store for many years], undated (Box OS, Photo number 50(VI):5)